Shochiku  Pictures
Dela's
Island
Paradise
ここはとある南の島　小さな村だが　実りは豊
Welcome to my island paradise.
The village is small, but it overflows with fruit.
由緒正しい王族にお仕えする　俺の名はデラ·モチマッヅィ
I am Dela Mochidis Gusting, a retainer to the
island's ancient and venerable royal family.
Dela Mochidis Gusting
占ってしゃべってモテるすごい鳥
I tell fortunes, I talk, and all the girls love me—
ain't never seen a bird like me.
Strike!
And strike!
And...
ちょっと休憩していいかい　デラ
Mind if I take a break, Dela?
こいつが幼い頃から俺が面倒見ている　この国の王子
This is the crown prince, Mecha Mochidis Gusting.
I've served him since he was a child.
Mecha Mochidis Gusting
メチャ·モチマッヅイ
この娘は国の占いをつかさどり
The girl is the royal augur and servant
to the prince, Choi Mochidis Gusting.
王子のお世話をしている　チョイ·モチマッヅィ
Choi Mochidis Gusting
おもちつきというのはなかなか大変だね　デラ
Pounding mochi really takes a lot out of you, doesn't it, Dela?
王子のもちつきは全然腰が入ってないぞ
You've got to put your back into it, my prince.
デラ　王子に対して失礼であるぞ
Dela, how dare you take that tone with him?!
はッ　口が過ぎました　チョイ様
My tongue betrays me, Lady Choi!
All you do is lie around and eat mochi!
もちを食べて　ゴロゴロしてばかりいるから
That's why you're so darn fat!
そんなにぶくぶく太るのだ
Forgive my fatness, Lady Choi!
ぶくぶくしてすみません　チョイ様
それに　ついたおもちは皆にも振る舞う
This mochi is for the people.
宮殿のみんなも楽しみにしているからね
They're really excited to try it.
王子　今度はチョイがおもちをつきます
My prince, let me pound the mochi in your stead.
いや　いいよ　チョイ
It's okay, Choi.
Exactly! Mochi pounding requires muscles!
そうだ　おもちつきは力がいるのだからな　王子がやれ
Keep going, my prince.
I swear, I'm going to cut off that tongue of yours!
だから王子に何という口を利く
Forgive me, Lady Choi!
すいません　チョイ様
いいんだよ　チョイ
It's okay, Choi.
ノドが渇いたね　何か飲み物を持ってくるよ
You must be thirsty.
I'll get us something to drink.
王子　チョイが持ってまいります
No, my prince! Allow me!
チョイ様はおもちを丸めねば
Lady Choi, your job is to form the pounded mochi.
Stop ordering me around!
偉そうに指図するでない　もう黙っておれ　鳥の分際で
Shut up, you stupid bird!
A pearl of wisdom, Lady Choi:
お言葉ながら　チョイ様
飛べる鳥はただの鳥　しゃべる鳥は貴重にございます
A bird with wings is but a bird,
while a bird that can talk is a treasure.
じゃあ　ちょっと行ってくるよ
I'll be right back.
あッ　はい
Yes, my prince...
今頃　うさぎ山商店街のみんなは寂しがっているだろうなぁ
The people of Usagiyama Market must be quite lonely...
俺がいなくなって
without me.
史織さんたちも
Not to mention Shiori and her friends...
お前のような騒々しい鳥がいなくなって
I bet they're relieved they don't have to
deal with your constant yapping anymore!
ホッとしていることであろう
もう少しあのもち屋にいてやってもよかったのだが
I wish I could've stayed at that mochi shop a while longer.
王子のお妃を探して旅に出た俺が
On my journey to find my prince a bride,
I ended up imposing on the owners.
ふとした縁で厄介になった商店街のもち屋
そこにはたまこという娘がいて
The eldest daughter was a girl named Tamako.
行かないで　デラちゃん
"Don't go, Dela."
"Don't stop me, my girl. I must go back."
止めるな　娘　俺は戻らねばならないのだ
島のみんなが今か今かと　俺の帰りを待ちわびているのだ
"My island people await me with bated breath."
分かったよデラちゃん　寂しいけど　頑張ってね
"I know, Dela. We'll miss you, but good luck."
"This is one of my finest feathers."
これ　いちばんいいとこの羽根だ
これを俺だと思って　いいもち作れよ
"I give it to you as a memento.
Keep making that delicious mochi."
"Thanks. I'll treasure it, Dela."
ありがとう　大事にするね　デラちゃん
あの娘がお妃様であると　チョイ様が言われた時には驚きましたが
Can you imagine my surprise when
you said she was the prince's bride?
まるっきり見当違いでしたな
You ended up being completely wrong too!
ご迷惑をかけてしまった
I really caused them no end of trouble.
皆さん　お元気だとよいな
I hope everyone is doing well.
さあ　おもちを丸めるぞ　デラ
Okay, let's start shaping the mochi.
同じ形ばかりでは面白くないな　もう少し独創的なもちを
Having them all the same shape is quite boring.
How about a little personality?
How's this?
チョイ様　どうです
何だこれは
What the heck is that?
ピーチもちですが
Simple peach mochi.
ピーチ　桃？
Peach mochi? Like the fruit?
チョイ様　まさかおしりと思われたのですか
Lady Choi? Did you mistake it for buttocks?
違う
No!
では　こちらなんかは
Then...
What about these?
いい加減にしろ
Cut it out!
デラ　私をからかっているのか
Are you trying to insult me?
I'm back.
持ってきたよ
王子みてはいけません
My prince! You mustn't look!
あッ　王子　どうだ　これ
Oh, my prince! What do you think of these?
Fool!
バカモノ
Oh, that's wonderful.
おお　これは素晴らしいね
すば　らしい？　このおもちが？
Wonderful?
Do you mean the mochi?
私は好きだよ
I like them.
王子もこのようなものが　お好き
My prince, you like such things?
Yep. I love them.
ああ　大好きだよ
そんな
No way...
それはデラもちだよね
They're Dela mochi, right?
はい
Huh?
Enough with the double entendres!
紛らわしいものを作るでない
ああ　すごい鳥でありながら　なぜかいつも不憫な俺
Treasure I may be, but woe is me!
耐えて忍んで青い空
Dry my tears, O sparkling sun.
青翼字幕组
莫奇玛兹王族使者团
何だこの野郎
What'd you say, bastard?
本字幕由青翼字幕组(http://www.qingyisub.com)提供
仅供学习交流之用 任何组织和个人不得公开传播或用于任何商业盈利用途
お前んとこのもちは粘りすぎなんだよッ
Oh, come on! Your mochi's too damn sticky!
お前んとこのはコシがなさすぎだ
At least it ain't limp like yours!
Forgive him, Dad.
すみません　お父さん
おめぇのオヤジはこっちだろうが
Your "dad" is over there!
I'm sorry, Dad!
すみません　お父さん　オヤジもやめろよ
Seriously, stop it.
Silence, my son!
うるせ　マイジュニア
今日という今日は決着つけてやるんだよ
Today's the day we settle this for good!
We live in a town market.
とある町の商店街
毎度
Come again.
いらっしゃい
Welcome!
味見してって
Step up and try some!
小さいけれど　にぎやかで　お祭りみたいな　この町で
It's a small town, but it's always lively here.
I've lived across from her ever since I was born.
生まれた時から向かい同士
同じもち屋の　息子と娘
Both our families make mochi.
Eldest son.
Eldest daughter.
たまこ
Tamako!
誰も気づいてないとは思うけど
I doubt anyone's noticed, but I sorta have...
僕はこの幼なじみの女の子に
恋を　してるんだけど
a crush on her.
いいよ　もち藏　どうぞ
Go ahead, Mochizou.
Over.
青翼字幕组
夕日が沈む　音楽室で
In the dusk
听  翻
零妖妖
梦游的庄子
茉莉
女巫
tasky
tinkyou
of the music room,
ピアノを奏でる　あなたの
you play the piano
I see your
柔らかい　横顔に
gentle face
校  对
buxuhoutui
kin桑
butt0n
总  校
馨柔儿
in profile
字幕·制作
青翼字幕组
惹きつけられて
I'm drawn to it
目が離せなくて
I can't look away
あなたの家の　テレフォンナンバー
I write down your
Kitashirakawa Tamako
telephone number,
繰り返し　書いて　覚えて
over and over to memorize it
Ooji Mochizou
受話器を　外して
I pick up
Kitashirakawa Anko
the receiver
Tokiwa Midori
ダイヤル回す　それだけなんだ
and keep turning the dial
Makino Kanna
without calling you
Asagiri Shiori
だ
だけど　そんな勇気も出せないから
Asagiri Shiori
时间轴
shiki
頓頓
后 期
晚安_地球
I can't muster up
け
ど
压  制
SkyJourney
the courage to do it
せ
せめて　この歌をあなたのためだけに歌う
I will sing this song for you, if nothing else
め
て
この歌は　あなただけに聴いてほしい
I know it's kind of an idiotic thing
制作
莫奇玛兹王族使者团
负 责
SkyJourney
だ～け～ど～
I can't muster up...
そんなこと言い出せないから
the courage to do it.
せ～のッ
One, two...
あいでッ　つ～ッ
Ow!
どうも　キャッチは苦手なんだよねぇ
I just can't get the catch right.
どうしたもんかなぁ
I wonder why.
必死につかみにいけば　とれるよ
You gotta grab it like you mean it.
そっか
I see!
Staff Lounge
失礼します
Excuse me.
いただきました
Good to know.
Excuse me.
失礼します
はいッ　では今日の練習はこれで終わります
All right, that's all for today's practice.
お疲れ
Good job, guys!
お疲れさまです
Good job.
Hold up!
ちょっと待った
Kanna?
かんな
遅れてすみません　そしてはいッ
Forgive my tardiness.
Now, pick me!
はい　牧野さん
Yes, Makina?
突然ですが重大な提案があるます
I have an important suggestion.
What is it?
何
実は　わたくし　かねてより　ひそかな野望がありまして
To tell the truth, I've always harbored a secret desire.
かんなちゃん　もしかして　まだ部長狙ってるの
Are you still mad about not being named team captain?
Of course I'm still mad about that.
もちろん　なれればなりたいですが
えッ
ではなく
But that's not it.
Here...
これに参加したいのです
We should sign up for this.
うさぎ山　マーチングフェスティバル
The Usagiyama Marching Festival?
申し込み　締め切りが今月中でして
The deadline is this month.
急だなぁ
That's kinda sudden.
第一　何の準備もしてないし
We don't have any time to prepare, and
we're not good enough to perform in public.
それに私たち　大会に出られるようなレベルじゃ
面白そうなんだけど
It sounds fun, but the market festival is soon,
and my folks need help crafting new mochi.
商店街のお祭りが近くて　新しいおもちを作らないと
Tamako, I want to create lasting memories.
たまちゃん　思い出を作りたいのです
思い出
Memories?
夏前には我々も引退です
We're disbanding at the beginning of summer, after all.
その前に　バトン部としての思い出を作ろうではありませんか
Won't you join me in making lasting
memories of our beloved Baton Club?
あッ　高い
Too high.
部長の私に　思い出をください
Please, grant your captain this...
Please!
かんな　部長は私
Kanna, I'm the captain.
Are you really going to spend
your youth shaping mochi, Tamako?
おもちだけを丸めて　青春を終える気ですか　たまちゃん
Huh?
おもちは一生丸められますが
Mochi will always be there for you to
shape, but our youth is ephemeral, Tamako!
我々バトン部の青春は　今だけなんですよ
たまちゃん
And...
からの　みどちゃん
Midori!
熱いな　かんな
You're really fired up, aren't you?
でも　いいかもね　うん
I guess it's a good idea.
皆さんは
What say the rest of you?
もちろん
We'd...
やりたいです
...love to...
部長
...captain!
ちょっ
Huh?
決まりましたね
Then that's that.
も～　まッ　いっか
Geez.
Okay, fine.
じゃあ　あと1か月
Let's work hard this month to put our best foot forward!
みんなで力を合わせて頑張ろう
せ～の
One, two...
おお～ッ
Yeah!
ちなみに　申込書はこれ
This is the submission form. Midori, do you mind?
みどちゃん　だしといてくれる
Okay.
オッケ　たまこ　キャッチ頑張らないとだね
Tamako, you gotta work on your finish.
No kidding.
本当だね
I gotta work hard.
頑張らないとな
Alrighty...
よいしょっと
何ッ　いきなり
What was that for?!
ちょっとかたいかな
Kinda stiff.
What was?
何が
「おしりもち」っていうのを考えててさ
I was thinking of making butt mochi.
What do you make of my butt?
たまちゃん　こんなのはどうでしょう
Oh, you don't mind?
おッ　いい
どぞ
Go ahead.
かんなちゃんのは歯ごたえよさそう～
Your butt seems pretty firm.
Would it make good mochi?
もちとしてどうです
Hmm...
ん～
みどりちゃんの　もう1回
Midori, let me squeeze you again.
Not happening.
ダメです
What? Please!
え～　ねぇねぇ　も～
Are you done with practice?
みんな　もう練習終わり
Oh, Shiori.
あッ　しおちゃん　たまちゃんの方におしり向けて
Turn your butt toward Tamako.
Just one more time.
もっかいだけ
えッ　何かついてる
Huh? Is there something on me?
No!
イヤです
Just one squeeze!
触らしてくりよ
No, but our dear mochi freak needs your help.
ああ　いや
うちの変態もち娘にご協力願います
ほれほれ
Come on!
どう
So?
えッ　何が
Huh?
What?
いけそう
Is it gonna work?
ん　いや～
Well...
That helps no one.
「いや～」じゃ分からん
She's glowing.
キラキラしてるよなぁ
Maybe it's the season.
春だからかなぁ
あれ　大路
Huh?
Ooji, what's this?
何だよ　これ
ん？　ああ
Oh, that...
大学　そこの映像科に行こうと思ってさ
College stuff. I was thinking of majoring in film studies there.
マジ
Seriously?
In Tokyo?
東京だぞ
北白川さんと離れ離れになるじゃん
You'll be so far away from Kitashirakawa!
分かってる
I know.
いいのか
You're okay with that?
いや　だから俺　決めたんだ
I've already made my decision.
何を
To do what?
あっ　な　何でもねぇし
N-Nothing!
What'd you guys put on your future plans surveys?
みんなは進路調査票に何て書いたの
「たまや」って書いたよ
Tamaya, obviously.
You're planning to take over after your dad? That's amazing.
やっぱりおうち継ぐんだ　すごい
たまちゃんの頭はもちだらけですから
Tamako's got mochi on the brain 24/7.
もちが人生か　人生がもちか
Life is mochi, and mochi is life.
じゃあ　将来はおもち好きの人を見つけるの
Then are you going to marry a mochi-lover too?
えっ　まだそんなとこまで考えてないよ
Huh? I haven't thought that far ahead.
史織は　やっぱ英文科
What about you, Shiori? English, I'm guessing?
うん　そう思ってたけど
Yeah, I was considering that.
But now I kind of want to study abroad.
留学してみるのもいいかなって
ハイ　シオリ　ハウアーユー
"Hi, Shiori, how are you?"
でも　向こうの生活になじめるかどうか分からないし
I don't know how well I can adjust to a foreign culture, though.
しおちゃん　とりあえずスルーは　なしで
Shiori, please don't ignore me.
あっ　ごめん　かんな
Oh! I'm so sorry, Kanna!
No problemo.
ノープロブレム　大丈夫ですよ
It's all good.
かんなは建築学科一択なんだよね
You're gonna go to an architecture school, aren't you?
うん
Yeah.
そっか　おうち　大工さんだもんね
I see. Your family's in the carpentry business, right?
でも実は私　高い所苦手なんだよね
I'm actually afraid of heights, though.
そうだったの
Really?
まあ　克服しますよ　いつか
But I'll get over it, eventually.
みどりは
And you, Midori?
私は　進学はしようと思ってるよ
I...
I want to go to college.
どこ受けようとかは全然決まってないけど
I don't know where to apply yet, though.
でも　地元かな
Probably somewhere close.
おじいちゃんのおもちゃ屋さんは継がないの
You're not going to take over your grandpa's toy shop?
考えてないよ
I hadn't even considered that.
Really?
そっかぁ
If you did, we could see each other every day.
でも　そしたら今までどおり　毎日会えるのに
じゃね
Laters!
また明日ねぇ
See you tomorrow.
Bye.
バイです
バイバイ
Bye-bye!
Everyone's got such big plans.
みんな　いろいろ考えてるんだなぁ
Good evening!
ただいま
よう　たまちゃん
Hey, Tamako!
ただいま
Good evening!
塩焼きがいいよ
Grill it with salt!
分かった
Good idea.
たまちゃん
Tamako, can I order ten stuffed mochi?
豆大福10個とっといて
Sure thing!
毎度あり
たまこ　おかえり
Hey, Tamako.
Good evening!
ただいま
Hey, Tamako.
おかえり
ただいま
Good evening!
おかえり
Good evening.
あっ　バトン部ね　大会に出ることになったよ
Oh, our Baton Club is entering the festival.
Wow!
みどりちゃん　張り切ってるよ
Midori's really excited.
そうかい　そりゃナイスだね
I see. That's great.
Kaoru!
かおるさん
くださいな
One, please!
はい
Coming up.
こんにちは
Hello!
いらっしゃい
Welcome.
デラちゃん　元気にしてるかなぁ
I wonder if Dela's doing okay.
何かね
It's now hitting me...
私ももう高校3年生なんだなぁって思った
This is my last year of high school.
いろんなことが変わっていくんだなぁって思うよ
Lots of things are going to be changing soon.
Today is always different from yesterday.
今日はいつでも昨日とは違う　だから素晴らしい
That's what makes it blessed.
そして　少し寂しい
But we will always pine for the past.
This enriches our lives.
その寂しさが日々を味わい深くする
Coffee is much the same.
コーヒーも　また同じ
Bitter!
にがッ
おっ　牛乳
Gimme the milk!
Hey, Mochizou.
もち蔵　おかえり
あっ　ただいま
Oh, good evening.
ただいま
I'm home.
おかえり
Welcome back.
ん
Hi.
Hey!
おう　引き出物のフォーエバーラブユーもち
That order of Forever Loving You gift mochi was for 80, right?
80個で　よかったんだよな
Yep, 80 Forever Loving You.
うん　フォーエバーラブユーもち　80個
Huh?
ただいま
Hey.
何だよ
What?
ぷいッ
気にしないの　吾平ちゃんもそのうち諦めるから
Don't let him get to you.
He'll give in eventually.
私はいいと思うよ　東京行くの
For what it's worth, I'm behind you going to Tokyo.
Yeah...
ん
それより　たまこちゃんには言った
Have you told Tamako?
はあッ　何で　別に
Huh? Why would I? I'm not...
You should tell her.
ちゃんと言った方がいいよ
分かってるよ
I know.
I know, dammit.
言うって決めたし
I'm gonna tell her.
いけねぇ
Crap!
たまこ
Tamako!
こ　こ　こ　こ
言おう
I'll tell her that I'm going to college in Tokyo at least.
とりあえず　東京の大学に行くことだけ
いや　もし　たまこが糸電話ちゃんとキャッチしたら
No, if she actually catches the cup this time...
Then I'll...
その時は　その時は
I'll...
キャッチした
She caught it!
100回に1回くらいしかできないのに
The odds were 100-to-1!
That's amazing, Tamako!
すごいぞ　たまこ
た　たまこ
H-Hey, Tamako, I...
あのな　俺　あのな
I'm not Tamako.
お姉ちゃんじゃないよ
もっち　私　あんこ
Mocchi! It's me, Anko!
お姉ちゃんじゃないから
Not Tamako.
えっ　なっ
Wha—
ななな　何であんこがいるんだよ
Wh-Wh-What're you doing there?
どうぞ
Over.
いいでしょ　いても
It's my house too, you know.
I just needed some lead for my pencil.
シャーペンの芯なくなったからもらいに来たの
Mine are all broken.
全部　折れちゃって
あっ　まあ　折れるよな
Yeah, I guess those things do break easily.
シャーペンの芯はな
What?
なに
Just like my heart.
まあ　俺の心も折れたけどな
Mochizou! Dinner's ready!
もち藏　ご飯
All right.
よし　明日の朝　学校行く時
Thank you for the food.
I'll just tell her on the way to school tomorrow.
いただきます
とりあえず　大学のこと言おう
そん時　話があるって　前フリして
I'll get her attention by saying we need to talk.
いってきます
I'm going out.
そのあと　やっぱり糸電話で
Then tell her the real news over the cup phone.
もち藏
Mochizou!
あっ　たまこ　よう
Oh, hey, Tamako.
What're you doing?
何やってんだよ
さっき　糸電話投げてきたんだって
I heard you tossed the cup phone over.
Huh? Oh, yeah.
えっ　ああ
Like, just use your cell already.
いい加減　ケータイ使いなよね
Look, they help connect your hearts...
あのな　あの糸電話はな　心と心をつなぐ　大切な…
あっ　もち藏
Oh, Mochizou!
何だ
Yeah?
Tomorrow morning...
明日の朝からさ
The Baton Club is going to start morning practice!
バトンの朝練するんだ
えっ
We're going to perform at the festival.
来月の大会に出ることになったんだよ
おお　そりゃすごいな　頑張れよ
That's great!
Good luck.
うん
Thanks!
応援　頼みますよ　もち藏
Make sure you come cheer me on, Mochizou.
Sure.
おお
ん
てことは　朝　話できねぇじゃねぇか
But then I can't talk to her!
あんこ　入るよ
Anko, you coming?
Yeah.
はい
ねぇ　あんこ
Hey, Anko.
What?
何
とうとう　おしりもちの試作にとりかかるよ
I've finally started creating my butt mochi.
どうせまたお父さんにダメ出しされるよ
Dad's just going to shoot down your idea.
そんな変なおもち
It's too weird.
You think so?
そうかな
Then what about mochi linked together
We'll call 'em Linked Mochi.
あっじゃあ　おもちを数珠つなぎにしたお数珠もちは
The old folks will love it.
おじいちゃん　おばあちゃん　喜ばないかな
Geez... You never change, do you?
もう　お姉ちゃんって本当お姉ちゃんだよね
先　行くね
See you inside.
えっ
Huh?
あんこ　もちっと優しくしてよ
Anko, you're so starchy!
もちだけに
Mochi needs love!
なんてね
Just kidding.
Oh, I forgot to take my contacts out.
あっ　コンタクトつけたままだ
I guess once won't hurt.
まいっか　今日だけ
Oh, sorry!
うわ　ごめんなさ…
ごめんなさい
Sorry.
ボ　ボイン
So bouncy!
Mochi.
もち
うん
あんこ
Anko.
何
What?
How about we sell booby mochi?
おっぱいもちって　どうだろ
人気出るんじゃないかあ
That'd be popular, right?
What?
はあ
Are you crazy?
もう　何言ってんの　お姉ちゃん
あんこ　私は真剣だよ
I'm being serious.
ぎゅうひでやってみよっか
Maybe we could add milk.
That'd make it soft, right?
やわらかいのがいいしね
I'm getting out!
私　先に出るから
Already? Did you even get a chance to soak?
あんこ
ちゃんと　あったまった
はいよ　もち藏
There you go, Mochizou.
ありがと
Thanks.
Mom's right.
そうなんだよ
Don't catch a cold now.
風邪ひくなよ
たまこには　ちゃんと言わなきゃ伝わらないんだよな
If I don't tell Tamako, she'll never figure it out.
We're now officially signed up for the festival.
ええっと
大会へのエントリーは無事　済ませました
じゃあ　まず　曲を決またいと思います
First, we should pick a song.
みんなが出してくれた候補曲を編集してきたので
These are the ones you submitted, so let's give them a listen.
とりあえず聴いてください
Ooji!
大路
おう
Hey.
おはあ
Heyo.
なあ　大路
So, Ooji?
What?
何
言った
Did you tell her?
Tell her what?
何の話
やっぱ　まだか
Not yet, huh?
やっぱなぁ
Knew it!
Totally called it!
だと思ったよ
だから　何だよ
Seriously, what?
Nothin'!
いや　何でもない
ちょっと　うるさいんだけど
Could you pipe down?
Sorry!
すみませ…
Come on. Let's go.
ほら　行くぞ
怖え　常盤
Tokiwa's scary.
I hear lots of people like being yelled at by her, though.
でも　常盤に叱られたいヤツいっぱいいるって
ちょっと分かるかも
I can see that.
貴重な経験
It's a very critical life experience.
もう　おめぇら　うるせいよ
Geez... You guys just don't stop talking, do you?
Sorry.
ごめ
Yoohoo!
Oh, hey, Midori!
あっ　みどりちゃん
Oh, I'll be right back.
ちょっと行ってくる
Okay.
オッケ　荷物持っとくよ
I'll hold your stuff.
ありがとう
Thanks.
よう
Hey.
You going?
今から
うん
Yeah.
Hey, Ooji.
大路さ
えっ
Huh?
分かりやすいよね
You're too easy to read.
何が
What do you mean?
たぶん　たまこはさ
You'd just be bothering Tamako.
そういうの困ると思うから
Seriously, I don't get it.
何の話だよ
You two have never been in the same class before, have you?
今までは　たまこと大路って
一度も一緒のクラスになったことなかったでしょ
That's why I never really noticed it.
だから　ここまでとは思わなかったけどさ
You're...
めっ
…ちゃ見てるね　たまこのこと
always staring at her!
What?!
はあっ　そんなに見てねぇし
I am not!
I just happen to look in her general direction sometimes!
たまに　チラッと視界に入ってくるだけだし
見てるよ　すごい見てる
You do stare!
でも　見てるだけだね
But that's all.
You circle her, like a shark.
大路はずっとそうやって　今までこれからもたまこの周りで
Always have, always will.
グルグルグルグルしてるんだろうね
しねぇよ
That's not true.
I'm going to college in Tokyo.
俺　東京の大学行くし
And I'm going to tell her.
それに俺　ちゃんとたまこに言うから
Huh?
Not anything you'd be interested in, though!
あ　いや　常盤には関係ない話だよ
When?
いつ言うの
じゃんけんぽん
Rock, paper, scissors!
I lost!
負けた
When'll you tell her?
いつ言うの
Today—
今日で…　んっ…
常盤　てめえ
Damn you, Tokiwa!
Today, huh?
今日　言うんだ
You're like a con artist.
勢い　余っちまったじゃねぇか
あれ　もち藏じゃん　どうしたの
Hey, it's Mochizou.
What's up?
Did he not make it to the bathroom? The poor thing.
トイレ　間に合わんかったか
かわいそうに
たまこ　大路がたまこに　言いたいことがあるんだって
He said he needed to speak to you.
えっ　何　何
What's up?
何かくれるの
Is it about my birthday?
Yeah...
He said it had to be today.
今日　言いたいだって
いや　別に　今日ってわけじゃ
No, it doesn't have to be—
さっき　そう言ったでしょ
That's what you said.
Come on, Tokiwa! Have a heart!
常盤　お前　カッパみたいな頭しやがって
Can we talk after practice, then?
じゃあさ　練習のあとでもいい
もち藏も映研あるんでしょ
You have Film Study Club, right?
We can walk home after.
終わったら一緒に帰ろうよ
あっ　うん　帰ろう
Y-Yeah, sure.
じゃね　あとでね　もち藏
Okay. See you then.
Okay. See you.
あっ　うん　あとで
今日って　今日かよ
Today?
Today?!
どうしたの
What's wrong?
Just a little disgusted with myself.
ちょっと　自己嫌悪
Huh?
えっ
イヤなの　自分が
I'm not happy with myself.
大丈夫
Don't worry!
私　みどりちゃんの分もみどりちゃん好きだから
I love you enough for two!
Okay?
サンキュ
Thanks.
よし　行きましょう
Okay! Let's go!
Yeah.
うん
おい
Hey!
どうしたんだよ
What's up?
大丈夫か
You okay?
Huh?
Yeah...
Ooji.
大路
何かできることないか
Is there anything we can do?
If you need our help, we'll be there for you.
何かあったら　いつでも俺たちを頼ってほしい
ありがとう　うれしいよ
Thanks, guys.
俺たちはずっと仲間だ
We're friends through thick and thin.
今までも　そしてこれからも
Always have been. Always will be.
小指に誓って
Pinky swear.
誓って
なんつって　なんつって
Dude! Dude!
That was perfect!
決まった？　決まった？
It was totally perfect!
めっちゃ決まったし　ばっちりだし
今の回しとくべきだった？
We probably should've filmed that.
べきだったぜ
Probably, yeah.
はい
Come in!
おじゃまします
Excuse me!
T-Tamako!
た　たまこ
Kitashirakawa?
北白川さん
I came to get you since we ended early.
迎えに来たよ
何か私の方が早く終わったみたいだから
あッ　こんにちは
Hello.
こんにちはッス
Hello!
外で待ってるね
I'll wait outside.
何があっても明日学校来いよ
No matter what happens,
we better see you at school tomorrow.
Yeah.
友達
Bros.
何　話って
What'd you want to talk about? The market?
商店街の話？
あッ　いや
No.
お店の話？
The shop?
No...
じゃなくて
あッ　おもちの話
Oh, mochi?
No way.
もちでもねぇよ
えッ　じゃあ何？
Then what? Are you filming something again?
また映画撮るとか？
いや　もちでもねえ　わけではないか
Well, I guess it's a little related to mochi.
もちと言えば　もち
I mean, it's not unrelated.
もち蔵？
Mochizou?
Yes!
そう　もち蔵の　俺の話
I wanted to talk about me!
飛び石だね
Look at the stepping-stones.
ああ　子供の頃　よく飛んで
Oh yeah, we used to play on them all the time as kids.
Yeah.
もち蔵　よくあそこで私のこと脅かしたっけ
You used to try to scare me a lot.
Oh, sorry. What were you saying?
あっ　ごめん　何だっけ
Uh...
あ　えっと
Something about you, right?
もち蔵の話だっけ
Yeah...
あッ　うん
あ　これいいな
This could work.
Booby mochi would look something like this.
おっぱいもち　こんな感じか
あのさ　こないだ銭湯ですっごいおっきいおっぱい
Last night, at the bath house,
there was this girl with huge boobs.
ああッ　もち蔵だったね　ごめん
Sorry, I keep changing the subject.
いや　いいよ
It's okay.
あれ
Huh?
もち蔵　話は？
Mochizou!
What'd you want to say?
Never mind.
もういいや
そうなの
Are you sure?
あのさ
Hey!
あれ　こないの
Huh?
You coming?
ねえ　もち蔵　この石　うちの豆大福みたいじゃない
Look at this stone. It's kinda like our stuffed mochi.
ほら
See?
It really is.
本当だな
Mochi are so small,
yet they can make so many people happy.
あのさ　おもちってさ
ちっこいのに　いろんな人を幸せにするんだよね
私なんか　おもちの何倍も大きくなったのに
I've grown up, but I still can't measure up.
まだまだ全然かなわないよ
やわらかくてさ
I'm missing that softness,
白くって　優しくって
beauty,
gentleness,
いい匂いがしてさ
and warmth.
あったかいんだもんな
Even the smell.
I wish I could be like that.
私もそんな人になれないかなって思ってるんだ
なれるかな
You think I can?
Oh, sorry!
あッ　ごめん　何か私の話ばっかりしちゃったね
I spun it back to me again.
たまこ
Tamako.
わ～　落ちる
I'm gonna fall!
たまこ
Tamako!
大丈夫か
You okay?
Thanks. That was scary.
ありがと　びっくりした
You saved me.
助けてくれるんだね　もち蔵
You wouldn't have when we were kids.
子供の時とは違うね
もち蔵？
Mochizou?
Tamako.
たまこ
I...
俺さ　東京の大学に行くんだ
I'm going to college in Tokyo.
とーきょー
Tokyo?
ずっと考えてたんだ
I've been thinking I should study film more.
ちゃんと映像の勉強してみたいって
だから　その前に自分の気持ちをちゃんと言っておきたいって
So before I go, I want to get this off my chest.
たまこ
Tamako.
Yes?
はい
俺　たまこが好きだ
I love you.
俺　めちゃくちゃ　たまこが好きだ
I'm madly in love with you!
So...
だから
Huh? Wait!
えっ　ちょ
Mochizou, what're you...
もち蔵　何言って…
Tamako!
たまこ
Pardon.
かたじけねえ
あっし　先に失礼するでござんす
I must take my leave.
えっと
What...
何だっけ
What'd he...
What'd Mochizou just say to me?
もち蔵は　今私に何て言ったんだっけ
それで私　何て答えたっけ
And what did I say back?
Mochizou...
もち蔵は　えっと…
たまちゃん
Tamako!
What...
たまちゃん　おかえり
Evening, Tamako.
たまちゃん？
Tamako?
どうしたんだい
What happened?
You're all wet.
ビショビショだよ
たまこ　おかえ…
Tamako, welcome back...
どうした
What happened?
おい　ずぶ濡れじゃねえか
Whoa, you're soaking wet!
おい　あんこ　何か拭く物
Anko, get a towel!
お風呂わかしてくるから　入りなよね
I'll get a bath started so you can warm up.
Pardon.
かたじけねえ
Why're you acting so weird?
何言ってんの　お姉ちゃん
Why am I hiding?
何　隠れてんだ　俺は
あッ　コンタクトなくしちゃった
I lost my contacts.
お姉ちゃん
Tamako, smoke's coming out of the pot!
お鍋　焦げてる
もう　信じらんない
You're unbelievable.
あッ　ごめん
Oh, sorry!
何　この料理　信じらんない
What is this? Just unbelievable.
This is supposed to be boiled mochi, right?
もちを煮たんだろ
えッ　もち蔵が何
What about Mochizou?
おもちだってば
He said mochi.
あッ　そういや　明日
Oh, Yoshida's got an order for 100 mochi tomorrow.
吉田さんとこから受けたもちが100あるから
もち蔵100個ね
A hundred Mochizou? Got it.
えッ？何言ってんだ　この野郎
The hell did you just say?
ごちそうさま
I'm done.
あれ　あんこ　もういいの
You're done already?
I can grill some Mochizou for you.
もち蔵焼いてこようか
すっごくいらない
Absolutely no way.
そっか
I see.
じいさん　醤油取って
Gramps, pass the soy sauce.
ほらよ
Here.
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Tamako
and
Anko's
Room
Anyone in?
入るね
はい
Just me.
あんこ　お風呂入りな
Anko, go take a bath.
はい
'Kay.
あれ　カバンがこんな所に
Hey, when'd my bag get here?
あッ　それ　もっちが持ってきてくれたみたいだよ
Apparently, Mocchi brought it over.
いてて
Ow...
Seriously, what's wrong?
本当にどうしたの
Are you sick? Your face is all red.
風邪　赤いよ　顔
あ　うん　風邪かもしれない
Y-Yeah.
Maybe.
今日は早く寝なよ
You better go to bed early.
そうするね
I will.
やっちまった
I've really done it!
Down we go.
Morning!
おはよう
Morning.
Sorry, I overslept.
ごめん　寝坊しちゃって
風邪なんだろ
I heard you're sick.
Go back to sleep.
寝てろ
あ　ううん　元気
No, I'm fine.
かしわもち蔵いくつだっけ
How many leaf-wrapped Mochizou do we need?
That's the most disgusting thing I've ever heard.
何だよ　その気持ちわりぃもちは
We need 50 leaf-wrapped mochi.
かしわもちは50
U
s
a
g
i
y
a
m
S
p
i
r
t
F
e
s
t
i
v
a
l
Ooba
Stewed red
bean
mochi
No date
Koyama
20 Daifuku
Abe
10 sets of red
and
white
23rd
Okawa
Daifuku
Miike
Leaf-wrapped
mochi
By noon on
the 25th
Red rice
お祭り用の紅白もち蔵もそろそろ作んないとね
Should get started on the red and
white Mochizou for the festival too.
縁起わりぃぞ　この野郎
Are you trying to get us cursed?
何でよ
Why?
もちが全部もち蔵になってるよ
You keep saying "Mochizou" instead of "mochi."
Huh?
おもち
Mochi...
Sorry, I think I'm still sick!
私　ごめん
やっぱり風邪みたいだ
いちにさんし　にいにさんし
One, two, three, four!
Two, two, three, four!
さんにのここで
Three, two, ready, and...
Turn, then toss!
ターンしてトス
どうかな
What do you think?
いいんじゃない
It's fine.
で　最後の最後は　イリュージョンで決め
And I was thinking at the very end,
we could finish with a magic trick.
イリュージョンやるんですか
Can we do that?
やるよ
ターンしてトス
Sure!
Turn, then toss.
ターンしてトス
Mumble, mumble...
見えた
Eureka!
Caught it!
いただき
さすがかんな　キャッチは外さないね
You never miss a catch, Kanna.
角度を計算しているので
I calculated the angle.
Really? That's amazing!
ええッ　本当ですか
すごい
I'm so sorry, Kanna!
かんなちゃん　ごめん
たまちゃん
Tamako.
ちゃんとバランスポイントを意識してますか
Are you focusing on the balance point?
一応
I think so.
まことにせん越ながら　たまちゃんのトスがぶれるのは
Forgive me for saying this, but I believe your tosses
go awry because you almost never focus on that.
バランスポイントをたまにしか意識していないからだと思われます
ボールと　ティップの間にある　このポイント
It's this point between the ball and tip.
Also keep in mind the angle of the fall.
あとは落ちてくるバトンの角度
どしたの　たまちゃん
What's the matter?
ボールがおもちに見えて
The ball looks like mochi.
さすが変態もち娘
You certainly are our mochi freak.
Only you would think that.
これがおもちに見えるのは　たまちゃんだけですよ
Okay.
はい　パターン気をつけてね
Remember the routine now.
Yes, ma'am!
はい
手首やわらかくね
Keep your wrists loose.
はい
Yes, ma'am!
See you after school.
ではまた放課後
うん
Later.
じゃあね
See ya.
おはよう
Morning!
Morning.
おはよ
おはよう
Morning.
やめろよ
Stop it, man!
You're hilarious.
おもしれぇ
何やってんの　たまこ
What're you doing, Tamako?
イ　イリュージョンの練習
P-Practicing magic!
Stop that.
やめなさい
What was that for?
何だよ
Essays in Idleness
"What a strange, demented feeling it gives me when I
realize I have spent whole days before this inkstone..."
つれづれなるままに　日暮らし硯に向かいて
Now this preface...
この冒頭
Did something happen yesterday?
昨日さ　何かあったの
Huh?
何もないよ　何もない
Nothing.
Nothing at all.
そっか
I see.
Yeah.
うん
行こ
Let's go.
Sorry.
ごめん
Upsy-daisy.
Something's different.
何かいつもと違いますな
えッ　別に違わないよ
N-Nothing's different!
たまちゃんのお弁当から漂う　この違和感
There's a strange aura coming from your lunch.
For there is no mochi!
何ともちがないのです
そういえば　いつも大福とか入ってるもんね　たまこのお弁当
That's right. You always bring stuffed mochi.
I just forgot.
入れ忘れちゃった
The mochi freak forgot her mochi?
この変態もち娘がもちを入れ忘れたとは
どんな事件が
It's the end times!
The end times!
事件が
I guess I lost my appetite for them.
ちょっと　おもちが苦手になっちゃって
あ　スランプですか
A slump, huh?
Slump?
スランプ
A mochi slump?
もちスランプ
I've had a nail slump before.
ちなみに私は釘スランプになったことがあります
Bam. Bam. Bam. Bam.
Back in grade school, I practiced hammering so
many nails that even the smell of metal made me sick.
小学校の頃　釘打つ練習しすぎて
金物のニオイが全部ダメになって
あー　何でもやりすぎはね
Too much of a good thing, huh?
Did you have too many orders or something?
たまこはおもちの丸めすぎ
Way back when, Tamako didn't even like mochi.
もともとたまこは　おもち苦手だったんだよ
Say what?
何ですって
Was that when you were a kid?
子供の頃
Yeah.
うん
Hey, dumpling-head.
もち屋のしらたま　北白川たまこ
Ooji-ya
The famous Usagiyama Ooji mochi!
Hey, dumpling-head.
もち屋のしらたま
Dumpling-head!
しらたま
Real original of him.
何とありがちな
That's so cute!
2人ともかわいい
What made you like mochi, then?
じゃあじゃあ　何でおもちが好きになったの
Well, once when I was really
depressed, it started talking to me.
えっと　すごく落ち込んでた時にね　おもちがしゃべったの
Don't cry!
泣くなよ
たぶんお父さんが
It was probably my dad.
That's so great.
へぇーステキ
But now you're in a mochi slump.
でも今はもちスランプ
Yeah.
When in a slump, one must steel their heart to overcome it.
スランプ
それは心を強くもって克服するしかありません
Huh? That's a little extreme.
えッ…っと　そこまでじゃ
I've just, like, got a bug...
ちょっと風邪みたいなものっていうか
A bug?
風邪
It'll pass.
治るよ　そのうち
Right?
だよね
Be careful not to make it worse.
でも　こじらせないでね
I will.
ちなみに私が釘スランプを克服したのは逆療法です
I got over my nail slump with reverse psychology.
I'd carry nails with me everywhere until the smell...
釘を持ち歩いて　常にそのニオイを嗅ぎ
Is it just me, or does your food smell like nails?
何かお弁当が釘のニオイしてきたんだけど
この独立戦争は
The Greco-Turkish War
was a series of battles fought by Greece against
the Ottoman Empire for the independence of...
オスマン帝国からのギリシャの独立を巡り争われた戦争です
Grampa, why do we run a mochi store?
おじいちゃん　何でうちはおもち屋さんなの
Because it's been handed down in the
family since my grandpa's generation.
おじいちゃんのおじいちゃんが　おもち屋さんだったからだよ
I know that already!
そんなの分かってるもん　でもどうしておもちなの
But why mochi?
Are you still talking nonsense?
また訳分かんねぇこと言ってんのか
What's wrong, Tamako?
どうしたの　たまこ
Why're you crying?
泣いてるの
Mochizou called me "dumpling-head"!
もち蔵がいじわるする
It's because you're so cute, Princess Tamako!
たまこ姫がこ～んなにかわいいからよ
かわいいかわいいたまこ姫
My cute little Princess Tamako.
Mochizou must love you a whole lot!
もち蔵くんはたまこのことが大好きなのね
It was leaders such as Jacques Laffitte and
Louis Philippe that started the July Revolution.
ジャック·ラフィット　ルイ·フィリップなどの指導者により
この市民革命は起きました
Also in July...
ちなみに7月に…
Here
Welcome, Tamako.
いらっしゃい　たまちゃん
I'll be back later.
今日はあとで来るよ
Good evening, Tamako.
おかえり　たまちゃん
ただいま
Good evening.
Tamako!
たまちゃん
Sayuri?
さゆりさん
You look well. I've missed you!
たまちゃん元気そう　会いたかったんだよ
I'll stop by Usa Bath tonight.
夜うさ湯行くね
うん　あとでね
See you then.
Good evening, Tamako.
たまちゃん　おかえり
Heya!
おいっす
Hey, Tamako. Want my extra?
たまこ　おまけのやつ食べるか
ちょっと待って
Hold on!
When in a slump, one must steel their heart to overcome it.
心を強く持って克服するしかありません
St—
こ
Steel my heart and overcome it.
心を強く持って克服
Hey, thanks, Mochizou.
おう　わりぃなもち蔵　ありがとよ
This thing's really hot!
あちーなこの野郎
As good as I remember!
やっぱいつ食べてもうめぇわ
Thanks! I'll be back!
ありがとな　また来るわ
Have another, Mochizou.
もち蔵　もう1個持ってきな
Usa
Bath
風邪治ったの
Are you better now?
Yep! I cured myself with willpower!
うん　気合で治したよ
Thanks for the bath.
ありがとう
Good night.
おやすみなさい
Thanks for coming.
サンキューな
Thanks, old man...
おっちゃん　ありが…
Tamako!
たまこ
It's Mocchi!
もっち～だ
H-Hey!
よう　元気かもち蔵　私は元気だ　じゃあな
How are you, Mochizou? I am fine.
Bye.
Morning! You're up early.
おはよ　今日早いね
Morning.
おはよう
Tamako.
たまこ
What?
何
Go rest.
少し休め
Huh?
You're not feeling well, right?
具合が悪いんだろう　店の手伝いはしばらくいい
You can take the day off.
Wouldn't want you getting hurt.
ケガされても困るしな
You haven't taken a day off since Hinako—your mom passed.
お前　ひなこ…
母さんがいなくなってから　一度も休んだことないだろう
It'll do you good.
たまにはいい
Okay, I will.
そうさせてもらおうかな
Thanks, Dad.
ありがと　お父さん
Down you go.
Oh.
あら
Good morning, Tamako!
たまちゃん　おはよー
Good morning.
おはよー
You're up early. On a walk?
早いねぇ　お散歩
Oh?
あれ　たまちゃんおはよう
Good morning, Tamako.
Tamako!
たまちゃん
Good morning!
おはよう　今日は晴れるぜ
It's gonna be sunny today!
Yeah.
Why hello, Tamako.
あれ　たまちゃん
Up early, aren't you?
早いね　おはよう
Tamako!
たまちゃん
Good morning.
おはよう
おはよー
Everyone's the same as always.
みんないつもどおりだ
What a beautiful day.
ビューティフォーディ
The same.
いつもどおり
The...
いつも
Mornin', Tamako.
たまこ　おはよう
いち　に　さん
One, two, three!
Midori...
みどりちゃん
I'm just no good at this.
上手に受け止められなくて　バトンとそれから…
Or at anything.
Is it Ooji?
大路
Midori.
みどりちゃん
Do you mind if I talk?
聞いてくれる
Go ahead.
うん
Mochizou said he's going to college in Tokyo.
もち蔵　東京の大学行くんだって
うん
Yeah.
The other day, when he said he wanted to talk...
こないだね
もち蔵に話があるって言われた日にね
He told me he loved me.
もち蔵に告白されたんだ
Yeah.
うん
I was surprised because he wasn't acting like himself.
いつものもち蔵じゃないみたいだったから
驚いちゃってね
When you asked me if anything was up, I said, "Nothing."
みどりちゃんにどうしたのって聞かれた時
何でもないって言っちゃってね
Yeah.
うん
So how do you feel?
それで　たまこは
I don't know.
分かんなくって
I ran away.
逃げちゃったし
もち蔵は　生まれた時からずっとお向かい同士で
Mochizou's lived across from me since forever.
His parents make mochi too.
おうちもおもち屋さんで
いつも　どんな時も近くにいて
He's always been...
right there beside me.
一緒に大きくなったから
We grew up together, so I didn't think
anything would change when we became adults.
何か大人になっても変わらないと思ってたんだ
だけど　もち蔵はちゃんと自分の進路とか考えてて
But he has a plan for his future.
He feels so far away now.
すごく遠い人になっちゃったみたいで
It confused me.
私はよく分からなくなって
But...
だけど
I think it's great that he's got a plan.
ちゃんといろいろ考えてて　すごいなって
I've kept the window and curtains closed this whole time.
部屋の窓がね　ずっと閉まっててさ
What should I do?
どうしたらいいのかな
I don't know.
分からない　私にも分からないよ
I can't answer that.
But I don't like seeing you down.
でも　たまこが悩んでるのは　あんましうれしくない
Sorry.
ごめん
Bug
There's a bug going around, so take care not to get sick.
今インフルエンザが流行ってるようなので
Bug
気をつけるように
Seriously?
Just so you know, my wife always brushes
after every meal, so we're both doing fine!
ちなみにうちの奥さんは
毎日毎日朝昼晩と欠かさず　うがいをしているので
とっても元気です
That also means I never go a day without
her cooking, which makes me very happy!
おかげで僕も毎日おいしいご飯が食べられて
とても幸せです
Let's start practice now.
はい　練習始めるよ
Yes, captain!
はい
Ow!
いてて
どうした
What happened?
I'm fine.
大丈夫
Tamako, you should take a break.
たまちゃん　少し休んだ方が
But...
でも
We can't have you spraining an ankle with the festival so soon.
大会前だし　足痛めたら
Okay.
うん
Oh, Tamako.
あれ　たまこ
Shiori!
史織ちゃん
Is practice over?
練習終わり
No, I just needed a break.
ううん　私だけちょっと
I see.
そうなんだ　私もこれから英語の塾
I was about to go to English classes.
And I forgot to mention that I
applied to study abroad this summer.
そうだ　私ね　夏休みにホームステイしてくる
Huh?
I don't know where they'll be sending me, though.
まだ受け入れ先決まってないんだけど
Oh, I was just really impressed.
すごいなと思って
I decided to just go for it instead of worrying endlessly.
留学するか悩むより行ってみちゃおうかなって
I'm nervous, obviously.
ちょっと不安だけど
But everyone has to start somewhere, right?
でも最初は誰でも何もかも初めてだよね
Tamako?
たまこ　風邪こじらせちゃった
Did your cold get worse?
How about going to the movies this weekend like we used to?
ねぇ　日曜日は久しぶりに映画行かない
Sounds good!
うん　行こうか
Oh, Tamako. Good evening.
たまちゃん　おかえり
Good evening.
ただいま
Goodness!
やだ
I won a ticket to that event!
顔見せ公演のチケット取れた
Wow, that's crazy!
ええ　すごい
Good evening, Tamako.
おかえり　たまちゃん
Mind if I take a break?
ねぇ　ちょっと休憩していい
Go ahead.
ああ　行っといで
Okay, what about Bad Luck Mochi?
なあ　やっぱり縁切りもちはダメか
When you eat it, you have terrible luck.
もちを食べて縁を切るみたいな
Gohei, focus on making the mochi more positive.
もっと縁起のいいおもちにしてよ　吾平ちゃん
I was gonna make Mochizou test it.
何だよ　もち蔵のやつに食わせてやろうと思ったのに
Oh, Tamako!
おう　たまちゃん
Good evening.
おかえり
ただいま
Tamako, you could at least acknowledge me.
お姉ちゃん
「ただいま」くらい言いなよ
Oh, sorry.
あ　ごめん
What's wrong?
どうしたの
I was just thinking that everyone's got stuff going on.
なんかね　みんなにも
いろんなことがあったのかなぁって考えてたの
Everyone?
みんなって
Yeah, everyone.
ん　みんな
That narrows it down.
全然分かんない
In the dusk
of the music room,
you play the piano
Tamako.
お姉ちゃん
I see your
This is the song Dad wrote when he asked Mom out, isn't it?
これ　お父さんが作った曲だよね
gentle face
お母さんに告白した時の
Y-Yeah.
う　うん
in profile
Why are you listening to it?
何で聴いてんの
Huh?
えッ　別に　その
No reason.
I mean, uh...
I'm drawn to it
えーと　ごめん　ちょっと
Sorry! Let me listen in peace!
I can't look away
一人で聴きたいから
What?
I write down your...
Mochizou, can you go out and buy tofu?
もち蔵　ちょっとお豆腐買ってきて
Sure.
あーい
I can't muster up
the courage to do it
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Stars and Clowns
Records
Coffee
Has she been here lately?
最近　来てますか
No, I haven't seen her.
いや　最近は
I see.
そっか
Oh, thanks.
あッ　ども　あ
Can I have sugar, too?
お砂糖も
I guess I scared her off.
やっぱり　いきなりすぎたかなぁ
Totally.
すぎたよなぁ
若さとは急ぐこと
To be young is to rush.
Anything can happen before a spoonful of sugar melts.
スプーン一杯の砂糖がとけるのも
まてないくらい
The bitterness of regret is proof you tried.
後悔の苦さは　何かをした証
It all adds up, building character.
ひとつひとつ　味わいになる
Bitter.
にが
What happened?
オヤジ　何
Oh, well...
ああ　いや
Mr. Fuku collapsed.
福さんが倒れたんだ
Some mochi got stuck in his throat.
もちをノドに詰まらせてって
Wait a second!
あーッ　お前とは　口利かないだった
We're not speaking!
Is this really the time?
こんな時に何言ってんの
Grampa!
おじいちゃん
Where's Mamedai?
豆大は
He's still on delivery.
まだ配達行ってるの
Grampa!
おじいちゃん
たまこちゃん　もう安心だから
Tamako, it's okay now.
Any family that would like to ride along?
ご一緒されるご家族は
Just me and my sister.
私とお姉ちゃんです
Mochizou.
もち蔵
I'll come too!
あの　俺もです
You two follow by taxi.
2人は後ろからタクシーで来てよ
Got it.
分かった
It'll be okay. Let's go.
大丈夫だから　行こう
Excuse me! I'll be getting on, too.
すいません　俺も乗るんで
Kitashirakawa Fuku
I might've had a bit too much mochi.
いや　ちょっと　おもちほおばりすぎちゃったかな
Is that your version of pills?
もちと心中する気か
Stop it.
やめなさい
Sorry.
悪かったな
Don't worry. We're just glad you're okay.
いや　まあ　本当無事でよかったよ
Dad!
父ちゃん
Hey.
よう
Damn...
おい　何だよ　生きてんじゃねぇか
You...
You're still alive.
Don't write me off like that.
勝手に殺すんじゃねえよ
Thanks.
すまなかったな
Oh, it's no problem.
あ　いや
Damn that old man.
ったく　じいちゃんは
Oh.
あ　東京行くんだってな
You're going to Tokyo, aren't you?
Your old man makes me go drinking with him a lot.
吾平に何回も酒　付き合わされたわ
What do I do, Mamedai? My son's...
どうしよう　豆大ちゃん　うちのマイジュニアがさ
Pipe down! Get offa me!
あ　もう　うっせえ　くっついてくんじゃねえよ
Sorry.
すみません
You're a man.
男だ
If that's what you want, then go for it.
自分が決めたんならそれでいいだろ
I will.
はい
But...
でもまあ　帰ってこいよ
You better come back.
I'll go back when I'm done filling out the hospital paperwork.
私　入院の手続きとかしてから帰るね
We can wait for you.
終わるまで待ってるよ
I'll be fine.
ううん　大丈夫
Dad, you should drive them.
お父さん　みんなのこと送って帰ってよ
All right.
Yes, let's all get home.
そうね　私たち先に帰りましょ
Mochizou.
もち蔵　あんた　たまこちゃんとバスで帰って
You take the bus with Tamako.
Th-Then I'm staying!
お　俺が残る
Who's gonna drive, then?
じゃあ　誰が運転するんだよ
I'm hungry. Can we hurry?
おなか空いちゃった　早く帰りたい
You two! Come straight home, you hear me?
おい　おめぇら　まっすぐ帰ってこいよ
Michiko, Gohei, thanks again!
道子さん　吾平さん　本当にありがとね
Um...
えっと　もち蔵　ごめんねびっくりさせちゃって
Sorry we scared you, Mochizou.
And thanks.
ありがとね　どうしようかと思っちゃった
I was really worried...
Hey.
あのさ
I'm sorry for the other day.
この間は　ごめんな
It's okay.
ううん
You can pretend it never happened.
あれさ　なかったことにしてくれていいからさ
Huh?
Just forget it.
気にしないでいいよ　今までどおりで
We can go back to how it was.
Yeah.
うん　いままでどおりでいこう
Back to normal.
Did Grampa get to eat dinner?
おじいちゃん　もうご飯　食べたかな
食ったろ
Of course.
What's hospital food like?
病院のご飯で　どんなの
You can ask him tomorrow.
明日　聞いてみろ
Oh, right.
そっか
Tamako, are you coming with me?
お姉ちゃんも　お見舞い行くよね
Tamako!
お姉ちゃん
What was that?
ああ　何
Are you coming to see Grampa with me?
お見舞い　おじいちゃんの
Yeah, sure.
ああ　うん　行く
Once practice is over.
部活　終わってから行く
I can watch the shop tomorrow.
Happy
Birthday
お姉ちゃん　明日　あんこがお店出るよ
Thanks, and sorry.
ありがと　ごめんね
Good morning.
おはよう
Mornin'!
おッはー
Sorry.
ごめん
Okay. One more time.
んッ　よし　もっかい
I'm so sorry. I know we don't have much time.
ごめんね　もう　あんまり日がないのに
I heard about your grandfather.
おじいちゃんのこと　聞いたよ
I know it's hard, but this isn't good.
大変なのは分かる
でも　困ったね
I just had a great idea.
いいこと考えましたよ
What?
何
I'll construct a glove lined with super magnets.
強力磁石入りグローブを作るのです
I'll add magnets to the baton as well.
バトンにも磁石をくっつける
Then, voila! The north and south poles will attract.
あら　不思議　ひきつけ合うS極とN極
あッ　しお   ちゃ～ん
Shiori!
More morning practice?
今日も朝練
What say you to north and south poles?
S極とN極について　どう思う
Huh?
Between them lies an unbreakable attraction.
どうしようもなくひきつけ合うのです
However, similar poles will reject
each other, causing the baton to fly.
間違えてS極とS極にしたら
バトン逃げてっちゃうので気をつけないと
What's the matter, Tamako?
どうしたの　たまちゃん
Did my lecture on magnets move you that deeply?
そんなに磁石の話がしみましたか
Yeah.
うん
えっ
You caught a cold, huh?
風邪ひ いたのか
It sucks.
やられた
I bet.
だっせ
When would someone say that they want
you to forget something ever happened?
人が1回言ったことをなかったことにするのって　どんな時
Shiori, you ignored me when we
passed on the bridge the other day.
しおちゃん　先日橋の上で私のことをスルーしましたが
I'm sorry. Pretend it never happened.
ごめんなさい
あれは　なかったことにしてください
Okay.
うん
Like that, I guess.
みたいな時じゃない
When things are awkward, and you
want the other person to move on.
気まずくって相手に全部忘れてほしい時　みたいな
I see.
そっか
Tamako, did something happen?
たまこ　何かあったの
大路くん　すごい　大路くん
Oh my goodness, Ooji!
You were really rattled when he said he loved you.
たまこ　大路くんに好きって言われてびっくりしちゃったんだ
That's why he asked you to forget it.
だから大路くん　なかったことにって言ったんだ
But you must be sad.
でも　たまこ　寂しいんだ
You love him, after all.
好き　なんだ
Don't cry.
泣くなよ　ひなこちゃんに笑われるよ
Your mom will laugh at you.
Mochizou?
もち蔵
Oh, that's cute.
あッ　かわいいね
I think it looked like this.
たしか　こんな感じで
A classic alien.
リトルグレイ
So what now?
で　どうするの
Don't you have something to tell him?
大路に返事しないの
What?
You have to tell him!
した方がいいよ　早く
Quickly!
What?!
A hallway run-in would be best.
やっぱ　廊下でぶつかりますか
Lie in wait for him behind a corner,
and when you see him at your 9 o'clock...
廊下の角で待機して
斜め45度に　大路くんが見えたら
Bam!
どしん　あッ　ぱたり
Oh!
Slump.
Block his way and start a conversation.
と　道をふさぐ
それをきっかけに
"Thank you for what you said. It made me really happy."
この間はありがとう
私　もち蔵の気持ちうれしかった
"I want you to build my house."
今度　私の家を建てて
Her house? I don't think that's related.
家　関係ない
That's what I'd like to hear at least.
私は　そう言われたい
That's so you.
かんならしい
I guess just telling him it made you happy is enough.
「うれしかった」だけで　いいんじゃないかな
Ooji!
大路
Mochizou, thank you for
you said! It made me really happy!
もち蔵　この間はありがとう　うれしかった
今度　私の家を…
I want you to build my...
Huh?
あれ　あれ？
貸しやがれ
Give me that.
Kanna, stop it!
かんなちゃん　ダメー
あッ　大路だ
Hey, Ooji.
What's up?
何
I didn't think you'd say it.
言えないと思ってた
Huh?
え
I didn't think you had the balls.
絶対　言えっこないって
But you do.
見直した
That's all.
それだけ
Sorry I'm late!
お待たせ
Don't mind if I do.
いただきまーす
Midori?!
みどりちゃん
Just kidding.
なーんて　大丈夫
I'm okay!
Thank goodness.
よかった～
You really like that song, huh?
好きだね　その曲
Huh?
えッ　ごめん　うるさかった
Oh, sorry. Is it too loud?
No.
ううん
I'm glad Grampa's okay.
おじいちゃん　何ともなくてよかったね
He said he could come back to the store tomorrow.
お店も明日から出られるって
Good.
うん
Hey, Anko.
ねえ　あんこ　これ着てみてよ
Try this on.
You're starting middle school next year, right?
来年からあんこも中学生だもんね
It looks good on you.
よく似合ってるよ　あんこ
Really?
そうお　ちょっと大きいけどね
It's kinda big, though.
Come here.
ちょっとこっち来て
There.
いいよ
Are you scared of change?
あんこは変わるの怖い
Where'd that come from?
どういうこと
I just feel like my world's really changed recently.
急に　今までと違う世界になっちゃうみたいな感じ
Dear Mamedai.
豆大さんへ
Huh?
えッ
What was that?
何
I wanted to give you something
back for making this wonderful song.
豆大さんがとってもステキな歌を私に贈ってくれたので
私も何かお返しがしたいと思いました
I, uh...
あッ　あの
I'm sorry for running away the other day.
この間は逃げてしまってごめんなさい
That's Mom's voice!
お母さんの声だよ
What?
This is my song for you.
それでは歌います
Twinkle, twinkle, little star
まぶしくひかる
Mom...
お母さん
In my heart, there you are
あなたのことば
She's not very good, is she?
ちょっと歌　下手だね
Up above the world so high,
まばたきしてる
No.
うん
でも
But...
Singing for just you and I
わたしのも  とへ
How I wished upon that star
わたしのうたは
That you might hear my little song
あなたのもとへ
Anko, I can work tomorrow.
あんこ　私　明日からお店戻れる
Good.
そっか
Good morning!
おはよう
Good morning.
Fifty stuffed mochi, please.
豆大福　50な
Okay!
うん
Midori!
みどりちゃ～ん
Morning!
おはよ
Morning.
おはよう
Midori, I think I can catch the baton at the festival.
みどりちゃん　私　ちゃんとキャッチできるような気がする　大会で
Sorry for worrying you.
心配かけて　ごめんね
I'll be sure to talk to Mochizou too.
ちゃんと　もち蔵にも返事する
Good.
だね
Let's go.
行こ
Leave it all on the stage, girls!
思いっきり　悔いのない演技をしよう
Yes, captain!
はいッ
うん
おす
Shout out your heart's desire!
じゃあ　いくよ　みんな　好きなものコール
Pancakes!
パンケーキ
Omelets!
たまご焼き
My crush!
センパイ
Angles.
直角
Bears!
くま
Mochi!
おもち
Ready, and...
せーの　お～ツ
Go!
Our next team will be the Usagiyama High Girls' Baton Club.
それでは　次の出場チームです
うさぎ山高等学校　女子バトン部の皆さんです
Empty Recycle Bin
Emptying the Recycle Bin
will permanently delete
these files.
Do you wish to proceed?
Cancel
Empty
Empty Recycle Bin
Emptying the Recycle Bin
will permanently delete
these files.
Do you wish to proceed?
Cancel
Empty
Inuyama
Answer
School's out?
Inuyama
Answer
休校
Inuyama
Answer
Yeah. Apparently a lot of students
have caught the bug going around.
そう　インフルエンザかかってる生徒が多いからって
I see.
そうなんだ
Ooji's the last on the list. Can you tell him?
最後　大路くんだから　連絡回しといて
Kitashirakawa?
北白川さん
あッ　分かった　ありがとう
Sure. Thanks.
Hey, Anko.
ねえ　あんこ
What do you think would happen if
someone wasn't told school was canceled?
連絡網って回さなかったら　どうなるのかな
Isn't it obvious?
どうって　次の人知らないままじゃない
They wouldn't know not to go to class.
Yeah.
うん
Here.
はい
Thanks.
ありごとう
Did Mochizou notice?
もち蔵　気づいてない
Not at all.
全然　今吾平ちゃんとテレビ見てるから
He's watching TV with Gohei.
Are you sure that's all you want?
でも　本当にそれでいいの
Yeah.
うん
Should I make you new ones?
新しいの作ろうか
No, these are fine.
ううん　これがいいの
Thanks, Michiko.
ありがとう　道子さん
Midori?
みどりちゃん
たまこんちに寄ったら　学校に行ったって言うから
I went to your place, and they said you'd gone to school.
I heard you didn't tell Ooji we had today off.
大路に連絡網　回さなかったんだって
No.
うん
He's not coming.
大路　こないよ
I ran into him.
さっき　大路に会ったんだ
He said he's off to Tokyo.
東京に行くって言ってた
He just decided it on the spot.
急に決めたんだって
It's pretty rash of him to transfer
to Tokyo in the middle of the year.
結構　思い切ったことするよね　いきなり転校だなんて
He transferred?
転校
But maybe that's better for him,
since he wants to go to college there.
まあ　東京の大学目指すんなら
今から行った方が　いいのかもしれないけど
He's taking the 9 o'clock bullet train.
9時過ぎの新幹線だって
You can catch him if you hurry.
急げば間に合うかも
Thanks, Midori!
みどりちゃん　ありがと
Midori.
みどちゃん
Kanna?
かんな
I was thinking of building some
new shelves while everyone was out.
いや　誰もいない間に　教室に新しい棚作ろうと思いまして
You're so weird.
何それ
What's with Tamako?
たまちゃんはどうしたんですか
She ran past me in a hurry.
さっき　すごい勢いで走って行きました
I may have lied.
ちょっと　ウソついた
Huh?
はい
I told her Ooji was transferring.
大路転校するって
All he's really doing is checking out college campuses.
本当は　受験する大学の見学行くだけなんだけど
Such machinations.
策士ですな　でも　そういうの好きですよ
I like it.
Hey, Midori.
あれ　みどちゃん
That's a good expression on you.
今　ちょっといい顔をしてますよ
Thanks.
サンキュ　かんな
I think I'm ready to climb some stuff.
ねえ　みどちゃん　私も高いとこ登ってみますかね
Huge, isn't it?
広いね
It certainly is.
広いんですなー
あ　たまこ
Tamako?
Dela.
デラ　春の香りがするな
I smell spring in the air.
Perhaps it's Tamako.
たまこの風か
Choi, Dela, it's snack time!
チョイ　デラ　おやつだよ
My prince!
王子
どっち　分かんないよ
Which way do I go?
How am I supposed to know?
Go,
行っけー　かんな
Kanna!
Mochizou!
もち蔵
Where is he?
どこ
Mochizou!
もち蔵
もち蔵～
Mochizou!
Tamako?
たまこ
Wait!
待ってよ
Wait for me!
待ってよ～
Tamako, why're you—
たまこ　何で…
Why?!
何で
Why...
何で　何で　東京行っちゃうの
Why are you leaving for Tokyo?
It's so far away!
遠いよ　東京遠いよ
いや　でも　えッ
But...
What?
What're you even doing here?
ってか何で　たまこここに
You've been by my side my whole life! Why are you leaving?
ずっと近くにいたのに　何で離れちゃうの
I still haven't told you...
私まだもち蔵に何も…　私…
Shoot!
間違えた
Which side do I take?
えっと　もち蔵　わたし
I...
私
I love you, Mochizou!
もち蔵　大好き　どうぞ
Over!
In the dusk
夕日が沈む　音楽室で
of the music room,
you play the piano
ピアノを奏でる　あなたの
I see your
柔らかい　横顔に
gentle face
in profile
I'm drawn to it
惹きつけられて
I can't look away
目が離せなくて
I write down your
あなたの家の　テレフォンナンバー
telephone number,
over and over to memorize it
繰り返し　書いて　覚えて
受話器を　外して
I pick up
the receiver
and keep turning the dial
ダイヤル回す　それだけなんだ
without calling you
I can't muster up
だけど
そんなこと言い出せないから
the courage to do it
せめて
この歌をあなたのためだけに歌う
I will sing this song for you, if nothing else
この歌は
あなただけに聴いてほしい
I know it's kind of an idiotic thing
I used to watch your innocent, smiling face
無邪気な笑顔　見ているだけで
as we talked for hours
延々はなし尽きないけど
ふいにだまって　時が止まると
But then you went silent
and suddenly seemed all grown up
急に大人に見えたんだ
I can't say I'm sad,
悲しいわけじゃないのに
泣きたい気持ちになるよ　なぜ
but I still feel like crying
Why is that?
If only there was a way to put this feeling into words
一言でも　伝えられるのならば
The shining night sky has begun to change
もう　変わりはじめている
あざやかな宇宙が
Spinning, revolving, calling out to me
廻り巡って　私を呼ぶよ
"Forget your shoes and run to the stars"
裸足でもいい　輝く世界へ
With the stars smiling upon me, I stretch out my hand
星がほほえんだら
手をのばし
小さく揺れていた心をただ　解き放つよ
And release my beating heart